[Music]
after a cancer diagnosis the focus is
understandably on monitoring the spread
and Resurgence of the cancer but you
know patients often also want to know
what additional steps they themselves
can take to support their body's fight
previously addressed what to eat after a
cancer diagnosis what about eating
nothing at all fasting is purported to
amarate cancers but to support such
claims they cite studies like this on
castrated mice that's because there are
no human studies of efficacy though
there are a few case reports for example
water only fasting an exclusively plant
Foods diet in the management of
follicular lymphoma traditional
chemotherapy has been the main state of
treatment for follicular lymphoma but in
the majority of patients the cancer
surges back with in a few years and the
chemo is associated with immediate and
enduring toxicities including secondary
malignancies meaning new cancers caused
by the chemo drugs themselves raising
the question of whether chemotherapy
should be abandoned for the disease okay
so anyway 42-year old woman presented to
her primary care provider with a
palpable mass in her groin and was
immediately sent for a CT scan surgical
biopsy confirmed the diagnosis of a
low-grade follicular lymphoma uh they
then found involvement in the lymph
nodes in her armpit which would make it
a stage three meaning spread throughout
the body uh because it didn't appear to
be aggressive she was just advised to
follow up every 3 months to monitor its
spread but she didn't want to just sit
around so she contacted the TR and Earth
Health Center in California to explore
medically supervised water only fasting
uh she' never smoked tobacco but she had
consumed the standard American diet so
they started her on a whole food plant
Foods diet of added salt oil and sugar
uh then she did 21 days on water only
before transitioning back to a diet of
Min processed plant Foods including you
fresh raw fruits and vegetables the
steamed and baked vegetables whole
grains and legumes and about an ounce a
day of nuts and seeds Okay so what
happened on physical exam her cancerous
lymph nodes seemed to be shrinking and
indeed on CT scan her enlarged nodes
shrunk up to 90% and no longer seem to
be active before
and
after what could it have been I mean she
did lose weight about 20 pounds but
folicular lymphoma does not appear to be
associated with obesity nor does BMI
appear to affect clinical outcomes it's
possible the plant-based diet alone
helped folicular lymphoma is the second
most common type of non- hodkin lymphoma
which itself is the most common type of
blood cancer in adults higher intakes of
dietary fiber whole grains and several
fruits and veget vegetables are reported
to reduce the risk of non-hot lymphoma
uh whereas animal Drive proteins and fat
in meat and dairy may increase it a
dietary pattern high in Meats fats and
sweets was associated with three times
the risk of folicular lymphoma or just
the fat and meat associated with up to
fivefold higher risk but why the thought
that foods of animal origin may increase
the risk of blood cancers originated
from the frequent finding of an
increased incidence among people who are
occupationally exposed to animals and
meats like livestock and poultry Farmers
butchers and slaughterhouse workers must
be acknowledged that animal foods are a
potential source of infection by cancer
causing viruses but it may just be the
animal protein excessive consumption of
animal protein May encourage malignant
changes through chronic persistent
stimulation the thought is that
continuous exposure to these form
proteins may act like a a chronic
irritant the animal protein theory is
bolstered by the fact that straight
protein casine milk protein increase the
number of lymphomas and rats but that
doesn't mean the same applies to people
maybe it's the hormones and antibiotics
contained in meat or just the saturated
fat which may both impair the immune
system and promote chronic inflammation
which may play a role in lymphoma now it
appears to just be animal fat
consumption so maybe it's just like
something building up in the animal fat
there may be a link between exposure to
Industrial pollut UTS and non-hot
Lymphoma and food especially meat milk
and fish is the immediate source of
almost all dioxins and pcbs in the
general population dioxinlike pollutants
build up an animal fat which can then be
passed along to Consumers vegetarians
may only be exposed to about 2% of the
dioxin dose compared to the general
population the highest single levels in
the US have been found in chicken but
thankfully the contamination levels are
declining in all meat across the board
furthermore consumers May further reduce
exposures to dioxin like compounds by
trimming fat before and after cooking
and by thoroughly draining fat from
cooked meat what about buying organic
meat title kind of gives it all away
when it comes to carcinogenic
contaminants the difference between
organically and conventionally produced
Meats were surprisingly minimal
exceeding the maximum limits regardless
of what kind of meat we buy strength ly
not only does the consumption of
organically produced meat not diminish
the carcinogenic risk but for some meat
it appeared even
worse what can decrease your exposure to
fat soluble pesticides is fiber and then
our good gut Flora can turn fiber into
berate which is absorbed back in our
body from the colon and acts as a tumor
suppressor demonstrated in more than 100
published studies including protecting
against lymphoma it also has potent
anti-inflammatory effects that may help
explain why fruit and vegetable
consumption has not only been associated
with decreased risk of developing
lymphoma but also been linked to
improved survival uh maybe it's all the
antioxidants in plant foods which appear
protective when it comes to folicular
foma but not necessarily when in
supplement form vitamin C intake from
foods for example may be protective but
not from supplements so the reason the
lymphomas and Cancers of the bone marrow
tissues are significantly lower in
vegetarians and vegans is not just
because of what they're
avoiding but all the goodies that
they're getting more of the
phytochemicals and antioxidant and
fruits and vegetables may inhibit tumor
progression via a variety of mechanisms
Beyond just the potential adverse
effects of meat so given the link
between fruit and vegetable intake and
Lymphoma survival maybe a lymphoma
diagnosis can be an important you know
teachable moment to improve diet in
patients that ly seemed to be the case
here at her six and emth followup she
reported strict compliance with her
whole food plant-base died and her lymph
nnes remained UNP palpable okay but this
was published 2015 how's she doing now
we'll find out next
[Music]